Guide to the Barbara L. Kevles Collection on Gordon Parks M1409
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Barbara L. Kevles collection on Gordon Parks
circa 1976-2001
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Kevles, Barbara L.
M1409
1 Linear Feet (2 boxes)
Interview notes and other material related to filmmaker and photographer Gordon Parks by journalist Barbara Kevles.
Kevles biography
Barbara Kevles has worked as a free-lance journalist for major publications for nearly forty years. Her articles have been published in many leading national magazines such as Esquire, Salon.Com, The Atlantic, The New York Times, People, Harper's Bazaar, Cosmopolitan, Glamour, Redbook, Ladies’ Home Journal, Good Housekeeping, US Weekly, New York, The Village Voice, Seventeen, Cineaste, Piano, American Record Guide, and Fanfare.
She has interviewed such famous people as Tom Wolfe, Kathleen Kennedy, Andy Warhol, Liv Ullmann, Jeanne Moreau, Judy Collins, Jerzy Kosinski, Slavko Vorkapich, Edith Head, Gail Parent, Joan Baez, Eleanor Holmes Norton, Stephen Hough, Andrew Litton, and profiled luminaries like Gordon Parks, Lowell Liebermann, Joan Kennedy, Eunice Kennedy Shriver, Sharon Percy Rockefeller, and Shirley Temple Black. Her critically influential interview with Pulitzer poet Anne Sexton published first in The Paris Review has been republished in six anthologies: Writers At Work: The Paris Review Interviews, 4th Series (Viking, 1974); Women Writers at Work and Poets at Work, (both Viking/Penguin, 1989); and Women Writers at Work (Modern Library, 1998); as well as Anne Sexton: The Artist and Her Critics, (Indiana University Press, 1978) and No Evil Star: Selected Essays, Interviews, and Prose: Anne Sexton, (The University of Michigan Press, 1985).
She’s also published hundreds of newspaper articles in such well known dailies as the Daily News (NYC), New York Post, Newsday, Fort Worth Star-Telegram, San Antonio Express-News, Austin American-Statesman, and The Dallas Morning News.
Collections of Kevles’ audio taped interviews, research, manuscripts, and correspondence reside at the John F. Kennedy Library, operated by the National Archives, Yale University Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Museum of Modern Art (NYC), Harry Ransom Humanities Research Center at The University of Texas at Austin, and Bryn Mawr College for the benefit of scholars, historians, authors, and students. Her Kennedy Library archives, which measure 1.5 linear feet, were used by Laurence Leamer in his bestseller, The Kennedy Women: The Saga of an American Family (Villard Books, 1994). See Kevles, Barbara L(ynne) at http://www.jfklibrary.org/Historical+Resources/Archives/Archives+and+Manuscripts [as of 2007]. Recently, Stanford University Libraries Special Collections and Art and Architecture Library jointly acquired a Kevles archive.
Kevles’ last bestseller writing book, Basic Magazine Writing (WDB), was a Book-of-the-Month Club and Quality Paperback Book Club choice and a Main Feature by Writer’s Digest Book Club. Basic Magazine Writing was endorsed by top editors at TV Guide, People, Family Circle, Harper’s Bazaar, and House Beautiful. It sold 2100 copies. She’s also co-edited an essay collection, In Opposition to Core Curriculum: Alternative Models for Undergraduate Education (Greenwood Press). Endorsed by Presidents of the University of Pennsylvania and Vassar as well as Harvard University faculty, this essay collection was excerpted in The New York Times and Change Magazine.
Barbara Kevles has taught at New York University, The New School (NYC), and The University of Texas at Dallas. Articles in basic forms she has taught, assigned and supervised by staff and free-lance journalists have appeared in The New York Times, Christian Science Monitor, Parents, Esquire, and People. Her alumni have worked for The Wall St. Journal, New York Post, Elle, Victoria, House Beautiful, and other notable publications. Barbara Kevles was educated at Bryn Mawr College where she received a Bachelor of Arts Degree. Kevles’ biography is included in Contemporary Authors.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Note that material must be requested at least 36 hours in advance of intended use.
Related Materials
Stanford Special Collections also holds the Barbara L. Kevles Collection of Computer Technology (M1588): https://searchworks.stanford.edu/view/6962501
Wichita State University holds the Gordon Parks Papers: http://specialcollections.wichita.edu/collections/ms/2013-01/2013-1-a.html
The Libary of Congress also holds a Parks collection: https://www.loc.gov/item/mm96083761/
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased, 2004. Accession 2004-005.
Scope and Contents
Interview notes and other material related to African American filmmaker, photographer & author Gordon Parks, created by journalist Barbara Kevles for two articles: "Gordon Parks, 'I don't make black exploitation films'", Village Voice May 10, 1976; and "Scenes from a Modern Marriage," interview with Gene Parks, third wife of Gordon Parks, Working Woman April, 1977.
This finding aid was created with notes supplied by Kevles about her interviews.
Motion pictures -- History.; African Americans in the motion picture industry; Kevles, Barbara L.; Kevles, Barbara L.; Parks, Gordon, 1912-2006
- Gene Young Parks, Gordon's third wife & his book editor; Executive Editor of the Trade Dept., J. B. Lippincott Company (23 5" x 8" cards) (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Carl Mydans, Life photographer (13 Cards) (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Scope and Contents
  Gordon from 1948 at Life, how Gene Young got to be his editor, his unusual photographic strengths, attitudes toward Muhammad Ali, Malcolm X
- Gordon Parks, Jr. (13 cards & questions) (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Parks' first born, also a film director, who filmed Super Fly (1972). Died tragically in an airplane crash in 1979 filming on location in Africa. Criticizes dad's films: "He takes the horror out of violence."
- Leadbelly Producer Mark Merson (8 cards & 2 cards with questions) (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Dr. James Barringer, Director of Minority Programming, Paramount (7 cards) (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Parks credits him as the reason Leadbelly got produced and that he prevented Leadbelly's production work from being stopped many times.
- Phil Kundhardt, Life Magazine, Assistant Managing Editor, and Managing Editor Special Issues (9 cards) (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Importance of Gordon as black for advice on stories like Watts Riots, Gordon's special eye, how lived with. Harlem gang, Flavio, to get joy & suffering, on film, 2 photo stories didn't run by Gordon & why
- Bob Williams, Farm Security Administration staff member (9 cards) (Box 1, Folder 7)
  how Gordon overcame blatant harassment of his photography & prejudice in Farm Security Administration photo lab workers
- Dave Golden, Hollywood cameraman on Learning Tree, both Shafts (2 cards); Village Voice editor Richard Goldstein (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Gordon Weaver, VP Marketing, Paramount (10 cards & questions on card front & back 2 cards on Shaft) (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Life editor Loudon Wainwright (6 cards & questions) (Box 1, Folder 10)
- More sources. List of awards Gordon Parks won (5 cards); Norman Whiteman, Paramount's Director of Distribution (1 card) (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Gordon Parks (9 cards #3 - #8 missing), 3/11/1976 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  Fracas in Detroit over Leadbelly... Depression... Insulted by Paramount marketing campaign & why
- Gordon Parks (21 cards & 1 card of phone #'s, 2 cards scheduling), 3/12/1976 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  How Ken Hyman at Warner/7 Arts gave first break in film, why Shaft was made, why sequels, why Leadbelly, Hollywood's stereotype of him as black director
- Gordon Parks (7 cards), 3/12/1976 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  Paramount cooperating, different audiences, different marketing. View of black man can die any moment, etc.
- Gordon Parks (5 cards), 3/13/76 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  Tennis style & strategy at tennis date, directorial style & intent of Leadbelly, story of Flavio, subject of LIFE Magazine photo essay & aftermath
- Gordon Parks (16 cards), 3/13/1976 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  Watching Gordon Parks play tennis & discussion with. him about tennis training & strategies
- 3/27/76 1 card questions 4/6/76. 1 card questions. (Box 1, Folder 17)
- 4/6/01 Gordon Parks (3 cards) (Box 1, Folder 18)
  Interview NYC train station, Leadbelly's performance, his direction of screen actors, Life ATTEMPT AT CENSORSHIP pof his essay on killing of Martin Luther King why left life 16 cards Philmfest director scene & stats
- Gordon Parks at Philadelphia radio station, WDAS (6 cards) (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Reception prior to screening at Philmfest '76 (2 cards) Gordon Parks on stage prior to screening of Leadbelly at Philadelphia Philmfest (4 cards) (Box 1, Folder 20)
- 4/6/01. Hotel Room Interview Gordon Parks (10 cards) (Box 1, Folder 21)
  Paramount's mistreatment of him, his son as film-maker
- Typed page of my memory of Gordon Parks' standing ovation end of screening (1 page) (Box 1, Folder 22)
- On meeting Gordon Parks at People Magazine 2nd anniversary party 2/26/76 (4 pp. single-spaced typed notes), 3/3/76 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  His battle with Paramount's racist marketing of Leadbelly with his comments
- Bob Williams Farm Security Administration staff member (4 pp. typed) (Box 1, Folder 24)
  Reminiscences of Gordon Parks working in 1942 segregated Washington, DC, working in the prejudiced Farm Security Administration. Discussion of Gordon's Job for Stanford [i.e. Standard] Oil that led to Life. signed by Bob Williams. w. letter also signed by Williams
- Village Voice agreement letter, article drafts (Box 1, Folder 25)
  Agreement letter to the Village Voice drafts: Editor's marked copy we revised in conference at Voice My copy of revisions made contemporaneously. Second article draft, First article draft
- My outline of article, Notes on relevant themes (Box 1, Folder 26)
- My Gordon Parks chronology (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Expenses (Box 1, Folder 28)
  Handwritten & typed list for Village Voice for trips for interviews with Paramount Marketing VP, Life photographer Carl Mydans, Ex-Farm Security Administration layout artist, Bob Williams Paramount Director of Minority Programming, Life editors Loudon Wainwright, Phil Kunhardt, Leadbelly Producer Mark Mereon
- List of phone numbers (Box 1, Folder 29)
  List of phone numbers of interviews Including those for Gene Young, his wife, Kunhardt, Wainwright, Mydans Williams, Gordon Parks, Jr. Paramount's Dir. of Distribution, Dir. of Marketing, Minority Program Dir., Leabelly producer, Gustav Rehberger, Sue & Bob Massey, David Gordon, Philmfest, Viking, a Hollywood writer, a cameraman. attached Gordon Parks signature? & home phone #
- Leadbelly news coverage (Box 1, Folder 30)
  Sunday News (Parks Interview) 76 Variety, "Par Rebuts Parks" 'Dillar Bias' Crack 76 Life, 1939 story of Leadbelly with handwritten note by Life Editor, Phil Kundhardt Letter from Philmfest: Leadbelly screening count Paramount Pictures Handbook of Production Information back: my notes on importance of Gordon's films Paramount Pictures New Ads for Special Audiences (white or black) Philadelphia Philmfest Program Booklet & Movie Lineup Program (Leadbelly opened fest) Philmfest Pin Undetermined publication (Parks interview & ape like ad) Detroit, The Sunday News Washington Sunday Star Long Island Press
- Leadbelly Reviews (Box 1, Folder 31)
  The Atlanta Journal Variety box office for Detroit Sunday Detroit News Hollywood Reporter 2 copies Playboy Undetermined publication Boston Notes on Paramount Distribution Variety 50-Top Grossing Films Variety Detroit Free Press Soul Endorsement Quotes Including The Village Voice, UPI, etc. Letter of Endorsement: National Education Association Letter of Endorsement: Manufactures Hanover Trust Co. UPI
- Gordon Parks Works (Box 1, Folder 32)
  Jazz, written & photographed by Gordon Parks- poem & essay on Duke Ellington, Original Life essay and Photographs by Gordon Parks: 'A Man Who Tried To Love Somebody' (His essay & color photos of funeral of Martin Luther King) Gordon Park's Life essay on "The Long Seach for Prido"
- Learning Tree film reviews (Box 1, Folder 33)
  Newsweek '69 Shaft's Big Score, The New York Times Learning Tree (book) undetermined publication Learning Tree, undetermined publication Learning Tree, Newsweek
- General Coverage Daily News (Gene & Gordon) (Box 1, Folder 34)
  75 The New York Times (Gordon reminisces about his life) Undetermined publication, Cicely Tyson, Shaft: The New York Times interview w. Gordon Parks Learning Tree: Gordon Parks interview, pub unknown Long Island Press, black films Shaft's Big Score, undetermined publication The Learning Tree, UPI This Week Magazine, Gordon Parks bio, The Village Voice, photographers make great directors from a Poet & His Camera, On Gordon Parks, Whispers of Intimate Things (Introduction) Kansas Qaurterly, Summer, 1976, Autobiographical Memories by Gordon Parks
- Copy of Working Woman, "Scenes From A Modern Marriage," (Cover Line Article) Published April, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  Introduction & Interview with Gene Parks, wife of Gordon Parks
- Background Research (Box 1, Folder 36)
  Questions for Gordon Parks, Paul Wilkes, Book Author, Helen Hanff, Book Author, Evan Thomas, Vice Pres., Editor W.W. Norton, Previously boss of Gene Parks. 7 hand-written pages of questions for Gene Young, Business Card of Genevieve Young, Exec. Editor, J.P. Lippincott Company (Gene Parks). List of Background Interviews & Phone Numbers (front & back) Hand-Written Interviews on a pad with Evan Thomas Helen Hanff Paul Wilkes Gordon Parks: as his editor, how he changed her clothing styles & attitudes, her fair play, his tearing up 100 pages & starting again because of her, dedication for her authors & sacrifice, their work schedule conflicts, her bossiness about household tasks, taught him to speak out, her Long Island marriage, his indefiniteness about engagements. Justified by his creativity, he consults her on his speeches & talks to her about his work (never would 2nd wife), her insecurity: her clothes, her work interferes with their sex life
- Typed letter to Gene Parks from Barbara Kevles (Box 1, Folder 37)
  with my unlisted # & interview dates: 5/20/76 & 5/21/76. 5/12/76. Questions for Gene Parks Working Woman Interview 2 pcs. paper 3 white pages, single-spaced questions, "Questions for Gene Parks," dated May 20,1976. 3 gold pages, double-spaced questions, "Gene Parks Final Interview," dated July 12,1976
- Gene Parks (1 of 2) (Box 2, Folder 1)
  Verbatim answers from Gene Parks to Barbara Kevles' interview questions typed exactly as she said them, on 20 pages, typed single-spaced of yellow paper: age, birthdates, responsibility for sister's name, sister's ages, lonely childhood, punishing, overly disciplining nanny, never snitched, dad Chinese diplomat, Daddy's girl, their mutual pursuits, relationship to remote mother, family moves, dad's incarceration by Japanese in W.W. II & death, schooling, her high school success, mother's UN job & credo mother's metamorphosis after husband's death, Wellesley College years 1st job & how she advances w/o typing or steno skills, 1st marriage, their relationship, housework, division, differences met Gordon Parks in 1962, opposed to taking on his book, Gordon's daily calls, weekly lunches, her naive views of it, fled his first protestations of love, discussion of course of action & its result and her prolonged five year work for divorce, her sisters' jobs, her work relationship w. Gordon Parks & yelling at him, Gordon's disregard of age or sex if he can learn something, his quickness of mind, spendthrift attitudes about advertising for his books nurtured by unlimited Life expense budgets, the Gordon Parks she married, her contractual nature & his open-handedness & its negative, her overburned[?] lot in house and for his business, her management of his pension, investments, financial decisions & her resentment & her feelings she's the only coolie in the house, drawn to him despite his faults, for travel & freedom & wilder life as Great Neck (Long Island) housewife.. his call to her from Madagascar during her lunch w. new NY Times food critic, Clive Barnes, at the Sheraton.. drawn to him for his gifts... refers to herself as "the brains in the family" her attitude about his possible affairs during his travels or hers, her frustration w. his indecision about making plans, her disapproval of her travel for work he didn't take her advice on "Shaft's Big Score," with disastrous end, who shares what with whom, or doesn't & why she taught Gordon to voice his disagreements with her, her complete obliviousness to his being black, in anecdote Gordon's jealous suspicions of her business lunches, her influence on him to fight Paramount's campaign for "Leadbell"y as black exploitation film, his influence on her, Gordon as self-starter in Love, written when they lived together, how she got Gordon an agent that precipitated his leaving Lippincott, her subscriptions to cultural events & Gordon's reactions how she got 20 lbs. off Gordon & changed his diet & her 1/4 lb. butter binges, her dependence on his clothes sense for herself, Gordon's taste for himself good except for check suits his prevailing & choosing their apt. furniture all in one day at Bloomingdale's (very funny anecdote about their clash of wills), why their marriage works though Gordon resents the demands of her career, some weeks they don't have real conversation because of conflicting schedules. End of 1st 20 pp. of 1st Interview with Gene Parks
- Gene Parks (2 of 2) (Box 2, Folder 2)
  Second set of verbatim answers from Gene Parks to Barbara Kevles' interview Questions typed exactly as she said them, on 18 pages, typed single-spaced on yellow paper. Her favorite cookbook, her salary, her bestsellers as editor, her job responsibilities as Vice President of Lippincott & Executive Editor of Trade Dept., root of her honesty and her tactlessness, roots of her Independence & Influence of her mother's development & credo on her, her family travels en masse & what it's like, once a year childhood in Shanghai, Paris, Manila no. times in China, life as Great Neck housewife, cooking beef casseroles changes in dress from formal Chinese to pants suits, her repressed emotions... oriental distaste for emotional scenes of she and her sister, "Both of us stayed married five years longer because we hated scenes." Initial meeting w. Gordon Parks over his book as one of her first authors & what his attention did for her, Gordon Parks' like her mother, her unworldliness, Gordon's encouragement to dress American & their disagreements about her clothes: about his desire for a formal look and her casual chic, Gordon Parks' influence on her change in hairstyle strangers' diff. reactions to them when they travel, his overwhelming instant popularity at Jill Kremintz' tennis club in a day, her childhood book favorites, very revealing, divvying up of household chores dishwashing male/female roles in previous marriage, doesn't worry about not cooking Gordon's dinner when delayed at work, divvying up of rent, household expenses, maid problems w. Gordon at home working, her deal to do his business books, Gordon's live & let live attitude about checking acct., bitches about her larger share of housework & why she does it, whose approval she seeks, her clash with Gordon's cultural values about manners, the orderly life she gives Gordon & their clash when she's not the hausfrau, her inauguration of vacations in Gordon's life, her bossy nature & Gordon's passive resistance, his respect for her work at night & weekends, his resentment of her reading half an hour before bed, famous people she's met with Gordon, her retreat from press & celebrity bit at movie openings, advantages in restaurants being famous encroaches on their privacy & time, her way around Gordon's inability to make social commitments & problems it poses for friends & how it's part of Gordon being black & graphic example of it w. Gordon, Jr. her subscriptions to cultural events & her independent social life apart from Gordon, her adjustment when he worked in Hollywood and she lived in NYC as his wife, her attitudes about being a mother, Gordon's phone calls or hers interrupt their dinner but she resents Gordon's calls more, why people marry, who cooked soup when both were ill with flu. End of second interview with Gene Parks.
- Excerpt Gene Parks likes from Betty Rollin book or article, First You Cry (Box 2, Folder 3)
  Barbara Kevles' notation of important themes & pages in interviews 3 versions of introduction to article, last typed Work notes of Barbara Kevles "Read Interview I through...see letter for themes..."
- white paper, Barbara Kevles' author note for article end blue paper, list of themes & pages (Box 2, Folder 4)
  Final Draft of Introduction & Interview, "Gene Parks: Scenes from A Marriage," 31 pages, typed on Time-Life paper ruled for easy word & space counting, with hand-written corrections & edits by Barbara Kevles on typed ms. Many pages have different versions of the same page under the one paper clip
- Kevles notes (Box 2, Folder 5)
  Hand-written outline of interesting themes Typed notes of Barbara Kevles' impressions of important themes Typed notes on July 13, 1976 by Barbara Kevles of her impression of Gene Parks at outset and during Interview Saturday, May 22, 1976 Blue paper typed notes by Barbara Kevles of Gene Parks dinner & Gordon's housework Carbon Copy Typed of Barbara Kevles' Biographical Data for Working Woman article. Submission Letter from Barabra Kevles to Beatrice Buckler, Editor of Working Woman, accompanying Gene Parks ms. & noting next assignment to interview comedy writer, Gail Parent.
- Gene Parks (3 pp. on column-lined paper) (Box 2, Folder 6)
  Carbon Copy: Text Changes from Discussion with Gene Parks. (Unsolicited) 28 changes to introduction and interview, Gene Parks Interview: Scenes from a Marriage. pp. 1-28 Introduction and Interview unedited. Coral stickum on top of edits & ms, "Original." 2 white note pages hand-written notations on both sides dated 7/20/76...list of same Gene Parks; editorial changes listed above.
- Gene Parks Interview (28 pp. manuscript typed on Time-Life column, pages of introduction and interview) (Box 2, Folder 7)
  Scenes From a Marriage, without previously noted 3 pp. of typed changes, Text Changes from Discussion with Gene Parks, incorporated. It is the ORIGINAL Unedited manuscript. Red marks indicate places where changes notes above belong in the manuscript. This manuscript is the first typed copy. It obviously has been read by Gene Parks. She has written a few editorial questions in the manuscript in pencil. Coral stickum on top says, "Original."
- Gene Parks (original typed copy 4 pp.) (Box 2, Folder 8)
  Text Changes from Discussion with Gene Parks (Unsolicited). Each edit checked twice with red and black pencil. & 5th page of edits not included with carbon copy.
- Gene Parks Interview (29 pp. typed) (Box 2, Folder 9)
  Gene Parks: Scenes From A Marriage (revised) Carbon Copy The Introduction and Interview Incorporate all changes requested in Text Changes from Discussion with Gene Parks (Unsolicited!) & fifth.
- Parks interview & correspondence, Working Woman (Box 2, Folder 10)